Guide to the Paul O'Dwyer Papers AIA.069
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Paul O'Dwyer Papers
1957-1998
1980-1995
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
O'Dwyer, Paul, 1907-1998
AIA.069
5 Linear Feet in 5 record cartons
Paul O'Dwyer (1907-1998) was an Irish politician and lawyer based in New York City active in numerous Irish American organizations who frequently worked cases concerning human rights and progressive causes. He was one of the founders of the O'Dwyer & Bernstien law firm in Manhattan, often working workers' rights, human rights, and civil rights cases. Although his interest in progressive causes was broad, he was especially involved and committed to conflict in Northern Ireland in the late 20th century. The collection documents his personal, political, and professional activities, including personal correspondence, in which personal matters and relationships are inextricably intertwined with political activism and professional activities; subject files, which cover topics concerning civil rights, human rights, Irish American organizations, the Troubles in Northern Ireland, and the United Nations, with specific emphasis on immigration and human rights issues; and the records of the Charles L. Keith and Clara Miller Foundation, displaying the interconnected nature of human rights and philanthropy in the city.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into three series, all of which are arranged alphabetically. The series are as follows:
I. Personal Materials
II. Subject Files
III. Charles L. Keith and Clara Miller Foundation Records
Biographical Note
Paul O'Dwyer (1907-1998) was an Irish politician and lawyer based in New York City active in numerous Irish American organizations who frequently worked cases concerning human rights and progressive causes. He was born in Bohola, County Mayo, Ireland and later emigrated to Brooklyn, New York when he was 18. He was one of the founders of the O'Dwyer & Bernstien law firm in Manhattan, often working cases defending workers' rights, human rights, and civil rights. He was an active member of the National Lawyers' Guild, and served as the organization's president in 1947. He held numerous public positions, including New York City Council member and New York City Commissioner to the United Nations and Consular Corps.
Although his interest in progressive causes was broad, he was especially involved and committed to conflict in Northern Ireland in the late 20th century. O'Dwyer was a prominent member of many Irish American organizations that lobbied on behalf of nationalist causes and pressured American politicians to take a more active role in the peace process in Northern Ireland. In both an official and unofficial capacity, he focused on extradition and immigration cases. His older brother was New York City Mayor William O'Dwyer, and his son is lawyer Brian O'Dwyer.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Brian O'Dwyer (Paul's son) in February 2014. The accession number associated with this gift is 2014.007.
Appraisal
Based on the initial survey of materials at the O'Dwyer & Bernstien law firm, materials concerning personal injury and estate cases were not taken as part of this collection.
Related Archival Materials
Frank Durkan Papers (AIA 008)
Archives of Irish America Irish Republicanism Collection (AIA 022)
National Lawyers Guild Records (TAM 191)
Records of the American League for an Undivided Ireland (ALFUI) are held by St. John's University in Queens, New York (MC 55)
Records of the Bernadette Devlin Defense Fund are held by St. John's University in Queens, New York (MC 8)
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists of materials documenting the personal, political, and professional activities of Paul O'Dwyer, an Irish-born lawyer and politician based in New York City. Materials include personal correspondence, in which personal matters and relationships are inextricably intertwined with political activism and professional activities; subject files, which cover topics concerning civil rights, human rights, Irish American organizations, the Troubles in Northern Ireland, and the United Nations, with specific emphasis on immigration and human rights issues; and the records of the Charles L. Keith and Clara Miller Foundation, displaying the interconnected nature of human rights and philanthropy in the city. The collection not only documents O'Dwyer's life and interests, but also reveals the efforts of individual people and organizations who labor to make broad social and political change.
Northern Ireland -- History -- 1969-1994.; Human rights -- Northern Ireland.; Violence -- Northern Ireland.; Peace movements |z Northern Ireland.; Political prisoners -- Ireland.; Irish Americans -- New York (State) -- New York -- Political activity.; Lawyers -- Political activity -- New York (State) -- New York.; Ireland -- History -- 20th century.
- Personal Materials
  - Christmas Cards, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 1, Folder 2)
  - Invitations, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Personal Correspondence: A, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Personal Correspondence: B, 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Personal Correspondence: C, 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 7, Folder 6)
  - Personal Correspondence: D, 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Personal Correspondence: E, 1992-1994 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Personal Correspondence: F, 1991-1993 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Personal Correspondence: G, 1992-1994 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Personal Correspondence: H, 1992-1994 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Personal Correspondence: I, 1991-1993 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Personal Correspondence: J, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Personal Correspondence: K, 1991-1993 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Personal Correspondence: L, 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Personal Correspondence: M, 1991-1995 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Personal Correspondence: N, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Personal Correspondence: O, 1988-1992 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Personal Correspondence: P, 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Personal Correspondence: Q, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Personal Correspondence: R, 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Personal Correspondence: S, 1990-1993 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Personal Correspondence: T, 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Personal Correspondence: U, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Personal Correspondence: V, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Personal Correspondence: W, 1992-1994 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Personal Correspondence: Y, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Personal Correspondence: Unknown, 1990-1994 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Special Correspondence: Condolence Letters, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 31, Folder 30)
  - Special Correspondence: Kathleen O'Dwyer Memorial Correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 32, Folder 33)
  - Will, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Subject Files
  Scope and Content Note
  This series consists of an alphabetical run of subject files created and kept by Paul O'Dwyer. They document his broad areas of interest and activism, and are heavily weighted towards issues concerning conflict and human rights in Ireland and Northern Ireland. The series contains files on many of the organizations O'Dwyer was involved in that lobbied domestic government representatives for a more assertive American diplomatic presence in Ireland and Northern Ireland, including Americans for a New Irish Agenda, the Behon Law Society, the Irish American Unity Conference, and Irish-Americans for Clinton-Gore, amongst others. Prominent human rights, immigration, and extradition cases concerning Northern Ireland are also well-represented, including Joe Doherty, the Birmingham Six, and the Guildford Four and Maguire Seven. Friends and acquaintances present in these files were often allies in activism, and members of particular organizations often overlapped. This series also contains numerous files dating from O'Dwyer's work with the New York Commission for the United Nations and Consular Corps.
  - 1981 Memorial Foundation, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Action from Ireland, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Gerry Adams et al v. George Schultz et al, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Adams, John Quincy, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - American Committee for Ulster Justice, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Americans for a New Irish Agenda, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Amnestry International: Report of an Amnesty International Missiong to Northern Ireland, Jun 1978 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Amnestry International USA, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Archives Research, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Bay, James, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Biaggi, Mario, Jun 1993 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Birmingham Six, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Boyle, Francis, 1985-1993 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Brehon Law Society, 1990-1994 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Breslin, Jimmy, Dec 16, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Britain and Ireland Human Rights Project, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - British Brutality in Ireland by Jack O'Brien, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 5, Folder 6)
  - The Brooklyn Sun Interview, May 1980 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Callaghan, Jim, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Callery, Sean. "One Eyed Reilly", 1992 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Carrow, Owen, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Clinton, Bill, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - College of Advanced Learning (Mohill, Co. Leitrim), undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Columbia University Nurses, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Conde, Sergeant, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Congressional Record, Mar 11, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Coughlan, Anthony. "A Unitary Irish State", undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Cree Indians, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - De Valera, Eamon, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Doherty, Joe, 1985-1992 (Box 2, Folder 19, Folder 21, Folder 20, Folder 22)
  - Ellis Island, 1990-1992 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Extradition, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Finucane, Patrick, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Friends of Homeless Irish Children, 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Friends of Irish Freedom, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Fugazy, Bill, 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Gaelic Games Broadcasting, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Gibraltar Assassinations, 1987-1989 (Box 2, Folder 30, Folder 31)
  - Goshen, NY, 1987-1992 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Grosse Ille, 1984-1991 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Guildford Four and Maguire Seven, 1987-1989 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Hall, Michael: General, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Hall, Michael: Typscript, undated (Box 2, Folder 37, Folder 36)
  - Honorary Doctorate from College of St. Thomas, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Horse and Carriages, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Immigration Assistance, 1985-1988 (Box 3, Folder 1, Folder 2)
  - Irish American Partnership, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Irish American Unity Conference, 1992-1993 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Irish Commission for Prisoners Overseas, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Irish Council for Civil Liberties / Committee on the Administration of Justice, 1992-1993 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Irish Institute, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - The Irish Nation Newsletter, 1984-1986 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Irish National Caucus / Fr. Sean McManus, 1992-1993 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Irish Presbyterians, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Irish Protestants, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - King, Peter, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Kurdistan Forum, Sep 2, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Lemisch, Jesse. "Listening To The 'Inarticulate': William Widger's Dream and the Loyalties of American Revolutionary Seamen in British Prisons," Journal of Social History, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Lobbying Efforts Regarding Northern Ireland (Various Groups), 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 17, Folder 16, Folder 15, Folder 18, Folder 19)
  - Lynch, Paddy, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - MacBride Principles Coalition of Ohio, 1992-1993 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - MacBride, Sean, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Mayo Foundation, 1989-1993 (Box 3, Folder 24, Folder 23)
  - McCrudden, Christopher, "Affirmative Action and Fair Participation: Interpreting the Fair Employment Act of 1989," Industrial Law Journal, Sep 1992 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Medal of Liberty Awards and Protest, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Metress, Seamus P. "British Occupied Ireland: Dying Colonialism and Nationalism in Conflict", 1985 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Miller, Kerby; Doyle, David N.; Kelleher, Patricia. "For Love and Liberty: Irishwomen, Emigration, and Domesticity in Ireland and America, 1815-1920." Inaugural Lecture at NYU Glucksman Ireland House, Nov 5, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Moylan, Sean, before 1957 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - NECO Armenian Earthquake Fund, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - "New Ireland: The Irish on Prince Edward Island" Exhibit at the Prince Edward Island Museum and Heritage Foundation, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - New Ireland Forum, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - The New Nation, Apr 1989 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - New York Commission for the United Nations and Consular Corps: General, 1986-1990 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - New York Commission for the United Nations and Consular Corps: Articles and Press Releases, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - New York Commission for the United Nations and Consular Corps: Brehon Law Society Proposal for Human Rights and Civil Liberties in Northern Ireland, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 38, Folder 36, Folder 37)
  - New York Commission for the United Nations and Consular Corps: The Economic Impact of the Diplomatic Community on the City of New York, Dec 1989 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - New York Commission for the United Nations and Consular Corps: Resignation, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - New York Commission for the United Nations and Consular Corps: Swearing-in, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - New York Commission for the United Nations and Consular Corps: Transition Materials, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - New York Observer Article, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - New York State Commission on the Bicentennial of the United States Constitution, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 44, Box 4, Folder 2, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings: General, 1990-1995 (Box 4, Folder 4, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings: Featuring O'Dwyer, 1979-1990 (Box 4, Folder 6, Folder 5)
  - NGO Models of Conflict Resolution Casebook, Sep 1993 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Northern Ireland Human Rights Monitoring Office, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Northern Ireland Report, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Pat O'Connor O'Dwyer Forrestry Foundation, 1990-1991 (Box 4, Folder 11, Folder 10)
  - O'Gardhra, Nollaig, 1991-1992 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Paine, Thomas, 1978-1989 (Box 4, Folder 15, Folder 16, Folder 13, Folder 14)
  - Pastoral Letter on Catholic Social Teaching and the US Economy, National Conference of Catholic Bishops, Nov 11, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Perot, Ross, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Puerto Rico, Apr 1989 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Quill, Mike, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Quinn, Liam, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Sallins Mail Train Robbery Case, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Schomburg Center for Research in Black Culture (New York Public Library), 1991 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - St. James Church, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - St. John's University School of Law Golden Jubilee, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - St. Patrick's Day, 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Stalker Inquiry, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - "State Terrorism," The Irish Education Series, after 1981 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Szyferblatt, Jul 1993 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Tara Circle, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - "Terrorism and Human Rights: Counter-Insurgency and Necessity at Common Law," Notre Dame Lawyer (Lowry, David R.), 1977 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Time to Go! (Northern Ireland Campaign), 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Tyrie, Andrew, 1980-1984 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - US v. Henry Hillick, James Conlon, Francis Michael Larkin, Kiernan Francis McMahon, and William Westerlund, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Wagner Archives Interview, 1993-1994 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Winchester, England Case, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Wine, Judge Hubert C., 1993 (Box 4, Folder 37)
- Charles L. Keith and Clara Miller Foundation Records
  The Charles L. Keith and Clara Miller Foundation is a philanthropic organization that funds civil rights and immigrant rights projects and organizations. O'Dwyer was President of the foundation in the early 1990s. This series consists of memoranda from meetings of the foundation's Board of Trustees and a large number of proposals from organizations seeking funding, ranging from small, local projects to well-established organizations, such as the Southern Poverty Law Center and the Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center. Legal aid and civil rights for particular nationalities are particularly well-represented amongst the proposals.
  - Meetings and Minutes, 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Proposals: A, 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Proposals: African Burial Ground Monument, Aug 6, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Proposals: American Indian Institute; American Indian Law Alliance, 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Proposals: Arthom Films, Somewhere in Austria, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Proposals: Association of the Bar of the City of New York Fund, Inc., 1990-1993 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Proposals: B, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Proposals: C, 1992-1993 (Box 5, Folder 5, Folder 3, Folder 4)
  - Proposals: Center for Human Rights and Constitutional Law, 1991-1992 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Proposals: Center for the Study of Human Rights (Columbia University), 1993 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Proposals: Christian Appalachian Project, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Proposals: E, 1990-1992 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Proposals: East Harlem Tutorial Program, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Proposals: Forum for Peace, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Proposals: Friends of the Children of Lascahobas, Haiti, Inc., 1993 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Proposals: Friends of a Free South Africa, circa 1992-1993 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Proposals: Fund for Peace, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Proposals: Futures for Children, 1992-1993 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Proposals: G, 1992-1993 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Proposals: Habitat for Humanity, 1991-1992 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Proposals: Haitian Refugee Center, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Proposals: Highgate House (Charles R. Allen, Jr.), 1991 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Proposals: Holocaust Survivors and Friends in Pursuit of Justice, 1985-1992 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Proposals: Housing Works, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Proposals: Hurcled Center (Cameroon), 1993 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Proposals: I, 1992-1993 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Proposals: Indian Law Resource Center; Indian Youth of America, 1992-1993 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Proposals: K-L, 1992-1993 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Proposals: M, 1992-1993 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Proposals: Masonic Medical Research Laboratory, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Proposals: Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Proposals: N, 1992-1993 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Proposals: Native American Council, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Proposals: Native Hawaiian Legal Corporation, Jun 16, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Proposals: Natural Resources Defense Council, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Proposals: Nuclear Age Peace Foundation, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Proposals: O-P, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Proposals: Q-R, 1992-1993 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Proposals: S, 1991-1992 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Proposals: Southern Poverty Law Center, Sep 1992 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Proposals: State Council on Waterways, Jun 14, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Proposals: T, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Proposals: US/Israel Women to Women, Nov 1992 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Proposals: W, 1992-1993 (Box 5, Folder 41)